# 大爷好
Hey Da Ye
# 师父好
Master
# 你看你师父乐的
See how happy your master is
# 刚强好
Hey Gangqiang
# 今儿做酸菜鱼
Today we are cooking Suan Cai Carp
# 应网友的要求
According to the request of our fans
# 先介绍一下原料
Let’s introduce the ingredients first
# 草鱼一条
Once grass carp
# 酸菜鱼的老酸菜
Some Suan Cai
# 泡菜
Some pickled vegetables
# 这还有野山椒
And also pickled pepper
# 泡子姜
Pickled ginger as well
# 这些食材啊
All these ingredients
# 自由市场 超市
You can find them in the farmer’s market or the supermarket
# 网上都能买
Or online
# 怎么还搁点肉啊
Why do we have pork here?
# 因为在饭店做咱有汤
Because we have broth at the restaurant
# 在家做没汤
But not here at home
# 没汤但是也要吃出饭店的感觉出来
The pork is to have the taste at the restaurant without the broth
# 所以说来了一块肥的五花肉
So we got a piece of fat pork belly
# 借着窍门比店里的一点都不次
With this trick, the dish will taste no less than the one in the restaurant
# 现在开始
Let’s begin now
# 耍起来
Here we go
# 背开
Fillet the fish from the back
# 草鱼为什么用草鱼啊
The reason we use the grass carp
# 草鱼它肉比较厚
Is that its fillet is thicker
# 而且土腥味还小
It also has less gamey smell
# 你看从这背开
Look at how we fillet the fish from the back
# 唰一刀
One cut all the way through
# 对 贴着骨头 顺着骨头走
Yeah that’s right. Cut along the spine
# 呦 行啊刚强
Huh, you are doing fine Gangqiang
# 这块儿掀起来
Pull the fillet up when the knife arrives here
# 这垫着个抹布
Grab the fillet with a piece of cloth
# 它省的滑
So it doesn’t slip
# 走
Cut through
# 好
There
# 味道强
Good taste
# 下来了
Here goes the fillet
# 放一盆里头
Put it aside now
# 待会把黑膜再给它去一下
Later we’ll peel off the black membrane
# 把这半边再取了
Let’s fillet the other half
# 好
Alright
# 剁段儿
Chop the bones
# 好
Alright
# 这块就不要了
We’ll leave this piece off
# 一会洗洗
Wash them later
# 把这黑膜都给它洗下去
Get rid of the black membrane
# 对
Right
# 因为洗不干净的话
If we don’t peel off the membrane
# 也会有土腥味
The gamey smell will remain
# 也不好看是吧
Also won’t look nice
# 鱼骨冲着
Leave the fish bones rinsing
# 我给你把锅开开
Let me boil the water for you
# 可以
Thanks
# 锅开着我烧点水
Boil some water
# 待会焯酸菜
To blanch the Suai Cai
# 把这块鱼骨去掉
Slice the ribs off
# 鱼腹也叫肚裆 肚腩这块
The fish’s ribs, or belly if you want
# 对
Right
# 大爷他们菜(国宴菜)有一个烧土豆对烧肚裆的
Da Ye has a famous dish called stewed fish belly with potatoes
# 烧划水肚裆
Stewed carp belly
# 这水冲着点
Rinse the fish bones
# 草鱼呢它有些黏液脏东西
Carps have some mucus and it’s really nasty
# 把它一冲水以后就特别利索
Rinsing it can get it off
# 没有土腥味 下一步来做酸菜
No gamey smell. Let’s prepare the Suan Cai
# 处理酸菜
Let’s get pm the Suan Cai
# 叶这块它就切寸段就行了
For the leaves, just chop them to pieces about a centimeter
# 知道酸菜是什么菜做的吗
Do you know what Suan Cai is made from?
# 酸菜就是榨菜大头菜
Isn’t Suan Cai pickled turnip?
# 那上头的缨子吧那应该是
Turnip’s leaves?
# 我纠正一下
Let me correct that
# 这是盖菜做的
It’s actually made from Chinese kale
# 广东也用这个呀
People in Guangdong also use this
# 但是广东用这个盖菜呢
Just in a different way in Guangdong
# 它跟四川的盖菜还不一样
The Guangdong kales are different from the ones from Sichuan
# 它那肉特别厚
Its swollen leaf base is extra thick
# 它是长得时候叶少
But with fewer leaves
# 它是抱团长
And the leaves stay very close
# 现在咱给它片一下因为它厚
Let’s slice the Suan Cai because it’s too thick
# 哎对 它更容易入味
Yeah so that the flavor comes off easier
# 酸菜鱼的酸菜是灵魂
Suan Cai is the soul of the Suan Cai Carp
# 这些酸菜就差不多了
These Suan Cai should be enough
# 焯水
Blanch them
# 它有那种酸菜土腥味
It’s got a bad smell of the pickled veggies
# 咱们开始把小料给它切了
Let’s mince the seasoning ingredients
# 这边焯着水两不耽误
During blanching so we can save some time
# 加泡菜
Adding pickled veggies
# 是四川家庭式的做这种做法
Is a Sichuan family style for the dish
# 仔姜这炒出来以后是灵魂
The stir fried young ginger adds another dimension to the dish
# 野山椒小瓶的
Also some pickled pepper
# 你这酸菜差不多了
The Suan Cai is almost ready
# 就是把酸菜这个臭气给它焯出去
Blanching gets the bad pickling smell off the Suan Cai
# 这酸菜要用凉水冲一下
Flush the blanched Suan Cai with cold water
# 好挤干了煸一下
Alright, squeeze the water off and stir it
# 用油来煸炒一下
With some oil
# 这时候咱在锅里给它焙一下
Let’s stir it in the wok
# 搁油了吗
Did you put oil in the wok?
# 不搁油 干焙
No, just stir it with the heat
# 把这臭味儿给它逼出去
Get rid of the bad smell
# 这就是密招儿
That’s a secret trick
# 好多人就是没做这个的
A lot of people don’t know this
# 都直接就煸了
They skip this step and directly cook the dish
# 有的切完了洗吧洗吧直接就炒了
Some people just chop it, wash it and stir-fry it
# 得 把这水气给它炒出去
Alright, the extra water is heated off
# 肉片
Stir fry the pork belly slices
# 少放点花生油
Little bit of oil in the wok
# 这时候香气出来了
When the aroma comes off
# 这时候你看葱姜蒜
Put the green onion, ginger and garlic in
# 料得足
Much of them
# 这需要大火煸炒
The wok needs to be extra hot
# 香味出来了 煸出香味
I can smell the aroma now
# 这时候仔姜跟泡菜该下去了
Now put the young ginger and pickled veggies in the wok
# 要把他这个蒜气味也要炒出去
Also cooks the garlic smell off
# 泡菜的香味
The aroma of the pickled veggies is amazing
# 野山椒下去
Pickled pepper in the wok
# 这时候鱼骨头该下去了
Now we can put the fish bones in
# 当时那鱼骨头应该稍微轻轻的炸一下
We should have fried the fish bones first
# 煎一下最好你看这
Better simmer then first
# 稍微煎它一下
Just simmer a little
# 不能有水
No water on the fish bones
# 把它煸出香味来
Cook the aroma out of the fish bones
# 煸一煸它这汤容易发白
After stir-frying, the soup gets whiter
# 把这水汽也给它煸出去
Also heat the extra water off
# 这时候
Now
# 再把酸菜撒进去
Drop the Suan Cai in the wok
# 下料准确
Right timings for each ingredients
# 方法得当
Also the right process
# 你看这时候
See right now
# 香味都出来了
All kinds of aroma are coming out
# 烹料酒(黄酒)
Some cooking wine
# 你看顺着锅边
Along the edge of the wok
# 这叫烹调
This is how we cook the flavors
# 这样料酒(黄酒)的香味全烹出来了
The flavor of the wine stays
# 而且这里头乙醇也挥发了
And the alcohol volatilize
# 这时候该加水了
Now we can add the water
# 冲起来你看
The water should go over all the ingredients
# 开水最好
Better adding boiling water
# 这个不够开
This water is a bit cool
# 但是这也能冲白了
But it should still get us white soup
# 加了温水要是开水更好
Warmer or boiling water would do a better job
# 开水一浇
If you pour boiling water in
# 马上就开始冒白泡了
It will instantly be white
# 这会咱们叫它熬着
Let it stew for a while
# 这时候片鱼吧
Let’s slice the fish
# 这时候我开始片鱼了
Now I’ll begin slicing the fillets
# 安排的很紧凑
The whole process is well organized
# 有程序感
Like a program
# 大抹刀
Move the knife back and forth through the fillet
# 吃一块是一块
One slice at a time
# 一下
There’s one slice
# 两下吃了两块
That’s the second
# 吃了两片想三片
It’s so good that you would want more
# 巴适
Nice
# 安逸
Great
# 这时候蹲进去
Put them in a bowl
# 准备腌了开始
Let’s marinate the fish
# 盐
Salt
# 胡椒粉
Pepper
# 来点香油
Some sesame oil
# 这个味儿一定要加足了
The seasoning must be enough
# 这时候
Now
# 该鸡蛋清了
Egg whites
# 加蛋清起嫩
The egg whites will make the fish extra tender
# 鱼片吃到嘴里滑爽
It will be very smooth in the mouth
# 这时候不加蛋清了
Hold the egg whites now
# 先给他抓出黏度来
First mix the fish to make them sticky
# 对
Right
# 要把它胶原蛋白给它挥发出来
Mix them so that the collagen comes out
# 感觉特别黏了已经
It feels pretty sticky now
# 这时候该加蛋清了
This is when we add the egg whites
# 抓黏糊了
Mix them to coat them
# 开始来点玉米淀粉
Add some corn starch in there
# 锁住它的水分
To lock the water in the fish slices
# 其实红薯粉也可以
Sweet potato starch can also do it
# 红薯粉更滑
Sweet potato starch has a more creamy texture
# 上浆 腌制 非常好
Coating and marinating are nicely done
# 洗洗手
Wash your hands
# 切点小料
Mince the seasoning
# 这是蒜蓉跟葱花
These are garlic and green onion pieces
# 待会呲油的上面
Later on we’ll scald them with boiling oil
# 小葱也可以
Small green onions are also fine
# 搁了不到三斤水
I put about three pounds of water in the wok
# 今这个鱼大
We got a big fish today
# 这会咱们准备调味
Now let’s season the dish
# 赶紧调吧
Yeah do so quickly
# 准备调味了
Let’s season it
# 我跟大爷说的话
I was discussing it with Da Ye
# 一定要拿三条鲫鱼先煲汤
It’s better cook the soup with three crucian carps
# 这时候就开始加口了
Now we can adjust the saltiness of the dish
# 辣度都差不多了
The spiciness is almost there
# 这时候稍微加点盐
So let’s add some more salt
# 胡椒粉
Pepper
# 胡椒粉可以多来点儿
We can add a bit much of pepper
# 这差不多了
That’s about right
# 胡椒粉的辣
The spiciness comes from pepper
# 野山椒的辣
And the pickled peppers
# 辣度还是不够
But it’s still not enough
# 再加点胡椒粉
Some more pepper
# 加点白醋
And some white vinegar
# 让它挥发出来
Let the sourness heat off
# 挥发一下
Volatilize
# 是吧
Right
# 好
Nice
# 要不然你单搁这醋太愣了
Otherwise the vinegar will stand out weird
# 它愣酸愣酸的
The dish will become too weirdly sour
# 这会儿行了 把料捞出来
Now it’s ready. Get the seasoning ingredients out
# 捞干净了
Get all of them out
# 捞出来开始下鱼片
Then we can drop the fish slices
# 小点火 这都要托熟
Bring the heat down a little bit
# 火小一点儿
Turn down the burner
# 下入鱼片
Drop the fish slices
# 慢慢的用汤把浸熟 养熟
Cook them slowly with the soup
# 过去酸菜鱼呢
In the past, we used to cook Suan Cai Carp
# 就煮完了跟你这一样
Just like you are doing
# 他就不呲辣椒了
But we didn’t scald the pepper with oil at last
# 对
That’s right
# 先喝这汤
Let’s taste the soup first
# 现在江湖川菜它搁点
Now the Jianghu style Sichuan dishes have this new cooking method
# 搁辣椒一呲
Scald the pepper with boiling oil
# 好多啊这川菜它有江湖派
We use it quite often in the Jianghu style Sichuan dishes
# 江湖派 对
Yeah, the Jianghu style
# 这个白醋刚才加完了
We put some white vinegar in there
# 加完了就是挥发的正合适
Now it should already volatilized
# 如果说你要是想吃酸点
But if you want the dish to have a sour taste too
# 你可以再加点
You can add more vinegar
# 不想吃酸的这就可以了
If you don’t like it to be too sour, you can leave it as is
# 这时候就行了
Now it’s okay
# 开锅即成
Let’s get it off
# 出锅
Into a dish
# 喜庆
Looks so festive
# 吃一片是一片
Every slice is so good
# 呲油
Now let’s heat up some oil
# 这好油啊 花生油
That’s nice oil. Peanut oil
# 再来点香油
With some sesame oil
# 二合油
Mixed oil
# 这边烧着
Heat the oil there
# 把这辣椒稍微用水洗一下
Here we wash the pepper
# 这个时候
Now
# 蒜蓉
Garlic pieces
# 葱搁上
Green onions also on top
# 料得足
We need to put enough seasoning here
# 好 油锅热了啊
Alright, the oil is hot now
# 这休息的时候来这么一锅啊
If we can have a dish of this during day off
# 哎呦
Mamamia
# 蒜蓉给它稍微呲一下
Scald the garlic a little bit
# 这个时候把这辣椒
Now let’s put the peppers
# 搁这碗里头
In the cooking spoon
# 好这样你看
Take a look at this
# 稍微一呲
Scald like this
# 这辣椒
The pepper
# 说糊没糊
Is so close to being burnt but not
# 恰到好处 齐活
Perfectly cooked. The dish is ready
# 这酸菜鱼给师父
Now this dish Suan Cai Carp to my master
# 给大爷交作业了
It can be considered as my homework to Da Ye
# 江湖派
Jianghu Style Sichuan cuisine
# 酸菜鱼
Suan Cai Carp
# 齐活
Ready
# 酸菜鱼做好了
Now the dish is ready
# 师父亲自给盛的
Get some to my master
# 来点酸菜师父
Have a try at the Suan Cai master
# 行了
Alright
# 大爷先来 谢谢二伯
Da Ye first, thanks Er Bo
# 味道强 手艺强
Gangqiang is so good at seasoning and cooking
# 拿起鱼来就开膛
Fluent at filleting fish as well
# 开完膛就该做鱼了
Fillet and cook very smoothly
# 看大爷吃这个劲儿还是不错
The dish seems okay based on how Da Ye’s tasting looks like
# 相当的好
Really good
# 通过从大爷的表情能看出
We can see from Da Ye’s expression
# 这个菜做的
The dish is
# 其实咱们这么说
Let’s put it like this
# 过于辣的也不行
It can’t be too spicy
# 对
Yeah
# 这个味道是恰到好处的
The taste is spot-on
# 非常好
Very nice
# 我尝尝肉 啊
Let me taste the fish
# 滑 嫩
Smooth and tender
# 爽
Nice
# 上浆的手法
The coating
# 手法加上汆鱼片的手法
And also the process you boiling the fish
# 到位
Are perfect
# 我给刚强点个赞
I’ll give Gangqiang a commend
# 好谢谢大爷 谢谢
Thank you Da Ye, thank you
# 我给师父盛
Let me get some for my master
# 你给师父盛
Yeah get some for your master
# 行 好了
That’s okay
# 迫不及待
Can’t wait for it
# 总结性发言
As a conclusion
# 刚才大爷
Da Ye just now
# 夸的很经典
Gave a classic appreciation for the dish
# 好的全说完了
Alright that’s it
# 是吧
Right?
# 到我这就
For me
# 师父批评两句
My master gave me a few critics
# 中规中矩
That sounds about right
# 对 是不是啊
Isn’t it?
# 适合大多数人的口味
It fits the taste of most people
# 这个江湖当中不江湖
It stands out from the Jianghu style Sichuan cuisine
# 平凡当中不平凡
A normal dish, cooked to perfection
# 这就是我们心中的味道强
That’s also my description for Gangqiang
# 人家说味道强
People say he is “Taste Qiang”
# 就是强
He really is
# 谢谢师父
Thank you master
# 大爷给你点一个赞
Da Ye gives you a like
# 我给你点8个赞
I give you 8
# 好 谢谢师父
Haha thank you master
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you Da Ye
# 上桌开吃
Let’s dine
# 小语
Xiaoyu
# 哎
What?